<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title><![CDATA[i was once again flabbergasted]]></title><description><![CDATA[a modest attempt at data understanding and visualization]]></description><link>http://iwoaf.com/</link><generator>Ghost 0.6</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2015 14:51:01 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://iwoaf.com/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[the data of long distance lovers]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>It is a truism to say that relationship is hard to maintain. It might be even more difficult when the Atlantic Ocean separates them. But thanks to internet and those <em>big data</em> companies that feed themselves with our personal informations, we can now have a <em>real</em> relationship even with 5,</p>]]></description><link>http://iwoaf.com/data-of-long-distance-lovers/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">f4ef5798-0388-4dae-a238-74b3eb0cfa4c</guid><category><![CDATA[textmining]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[aDrz]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2015 12:35:11 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It is a truism to say that relationship is hard to maintain. It might be even more difficult when the Atlantic Ocean separates them. But thanks to internet and those <em>big data</em> companies that feed themselves with our personal informations, we can now have a <em>real</em> relationship even with 5,500 km between us. Real in sense of small talks, common projects, and fights... Only the means differ from the conventional relations as the acoustic vibration produced by the mouth is replaced by 0s and 1s traveling through transoceanic cables.</p>

<p>To illustrate this point, here some analysis of our daily discussions through the phone app <a href="http://www.viber.com/">viber</a>. Viber allows their users to get a nice and well formatted csv file containing the date, the sender, and the content of each message. So here's a few graphs that summarize it.</p>

<p><img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/08/nb_msg.png" alt="number of messages"></p>

<p>The log hold slight more than a year of data and exactly 20,846 messages, <strong>she</strong> is responsible for 51.2% of the total. The proportion of sent messages is decently equivalent even if <strong>he</strong> has sent 520 less of them.  Let's state that it is due to the more talkative characteristic of the girls in general...</p>

<p>It is interesting to continue the comparison between <strong>Her</strong> and <strong>Him</strong> with a focus on the time taken to respond to a message.</p>

<p><img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/08/time_to_answer-2.png" alt="time to answer a message"></p>

<p>I like the previous graph that shows that more than 60% of messages from <strong>Her</strong> and <strong>Him</strong> are answered within 2 minutes. However, we see that <strong>he</strong> has the tendency to let her wait more ! even up to more that 8 hours. The explanation to this trend is that most of this long answers are due to message sent during <strong>his</strong> night. </p>

<p><div id="wrapper-tbl"></div></p>

<p><table id="keywords" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0">
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th><span>Answerer</span></th>
        <th><span>Mean time to answer</span></th>
        <th><span>Median time to answer</span></th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td class="lalign"><strong>Her</strong></td>
        <td>38 min</td>
        <td>55 sec</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="lalign"><strong>Him</strong></td>
        <td>81 min</td>
        <td>54 sec</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
 </p>

<p>The table illustrates the huge difference between the mean and the median time to answer. From this we can say that 50% of <strong>his</strong> answers are made in less than 54 secondes compare to 55 secondes for <strong>her</strong> answers.</p>

<p>Comparison is no longer needed as the viber log is common and loving conversation between two persons ! So let's talk about the global statistics of this one year apart exchanged messages.</p>

<p><img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/08/n_char-3.png" alt="histogram number of character"></p>

<p>No surprise here for the histogram of the number of characters per messages. Majority of the messages are tiny, less than 15 characters. We also see that at least 10% of the messages contains 4 or less characters. Most of the time small messages are quickly sent and are more than enough! Those are mostly smileys, "yep", "hehe", "oui", "yes" and some lonely punctuations.</p>

<p>Speaking of small words, it is funny to focus on our language of of laughter and lover. The following to pie charts perform a similar <a href="https://research.facebook.com/blog/1605690073053884/the-not-so-universal-language-of-laughter/">facebook</a> study of how we express laugh or love with instant messaging. For the laugh, our result slightly differ from the facebook one as the proportion of the "haha" are lower, and the one of the "lol" are bigger than expected. Facebook would qualified us as <em>hehe-er</em>. <br>
In term of e-love, we mostly send "bisous" or "kisses", but some "cuddles" and "smacks" are also part of our e-love vocabulary.</p>

<p><img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/08/e-laugh.png" alt="drawing" title=""><img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/08/e-love-2.png" alt="drawing" title=""></p>

<p>The following figure groups the messages by their hours and reports it as an histogram. Most of the messages are sent at the end of the day (6:00pm to midnight). Let's note that the time used by the log are the one from Paris and explains that almost no messages are sent between 1:00am and 7:00am as those hours are commonly used to sleep. Similarly no messages are exchange between 8:00pm and 1:00pm as it is also sleep time in Boston (6 hours of difference). </p>

<p><img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/08/hist-hours-3.png" alt="histo hours"></p>

<p>Here is a calendar with the number of messages shared for each day. The more red the day is, the more text were sent. Usually, less than 50 messages are sent each days. One this graph, we see blank days in August 2014, Christmas 2014, May 2015, and August 2015, those are obviously time spent together in real life !</p>

<p><img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/08/calendar-day-1.png" alt="calendar plot log"></p>

<p>Finally let's have a look at the most used words in the conversations. In the word cloud, the size of the word are a proxy for its frequency, the color groups the words with similar frequency. So purple is for the most used words, then in decreasing order we have green, blue, and red.  </p>

<p><img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/08/wordcloudtt.png" alt=""></p>

<p>As a bonus, here is the two personal wordcloud: </p>

<p><img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/08/wordcloud-her-2.png" alt="drawing" title=""><img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/08/wordcloud-him-2.png" alt="drawing" title=""></p>

<p>The code that generates all the graphs are available on my <a href="https://github.com/aDrz/analysis-viber-logs">github</a>. However the csv file is not public for obvious reasons.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[old but still impressive]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cjAqR1zICA0">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cjAqR1zICA0</a></p>]]></description><link>http://iwoaf.com/old-but-still-impressive/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">9582fb45-6020-4104-a4b5-9ef3075e038c</guid><category><![CDATA[external]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[aDrz]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2015 13:24:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cjAqR1zICA0">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cjAqR1zICA0</a></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[plot large time series with R]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Trying to plot a huge time series in R is messy. It takes ages to have the plot rendered and the saved pdf wants to eat my hard-disk.</p>

<p>As our screen has limited number of pixels, we do not really need to plot all the data points. However a simple</p>]]></description><link>http://iwoaf.com/plot-large-time-series-with-r/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">c652cb70-e4a4-4b2d-8f34-e22d6b41441d</guid><category><![CDATA[R]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[aDrz]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2015 13:21:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Trying to plot a huge time series in R is messy. It takes ages to have the plot rendered and the saved pdf wants to eat my hard-disk.</p>

<p>As our screen has limited number of pixels, we do not really need to plot all the data points. However a simple downsampling (take a point each n points) does not fit my requirements as it remove high frequency content from the signal <a href="https://stat.ethz.ch/pipermail/r-help/2011-October/294004.html">link</a>.</p>

<p>A solution is to take the large univariate time series and transform it into a bivariate time series with the min and the max over successive blocks. Thus instead of plotting N concentrate overlapping points, the idea is to only plot the max and the min of these overlapping points.</p>

<p>The R snippet here:</p>

<pre><code class="language-r"># Large time series compression for plot
ts.compress &lt;- function(x, start=NULL, n=2^10)  
{
  p &lt;- length(x)
  l &lt;- floor(p/n)
  if (p&lt;n){
      return(x)
  }else {
    y  &lt;- matrix(as.numeric(x[1:(l*n)]),n,l,byrow=TRUE)
    y.min &lt;- apply(y, 1, min) 
    y.max &lt;- apply(y, 1, max)
    y.minmax &lt;- matrix(rbind(y.min,y.max),2*n,1,byrow=FALSE)
    return(ts(y.minmax, frequency=frequency(x)*2/l, start=start))
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>So let's try it</p>

<pre><code class="language-r"># Simulation of a time large dataset
set.seed(120)  
data &lt;- ts(cumsum(rnorm(2**20)), start=c(1946,1), frequency = 24*60*60)  
data.compress &lt;- ts.compress(data, start=c(1946,1))

# The plot
pdf('~/tmp/rplot.pdf',width = 8, height = 4)  
plot(data)  
dev.off()  
pdf('~/tmp/rplot-compress.pdf',width = 8, height = 4)  
plot(data.compress)  
dev.off()  
</code></pre>

<p>Results in <a href="https://github.com/aDrz/adrz.github.io/raw/master/content/images/rplot.pdf">rplot.pdf</a> (2.1 Mo) and <a href="https://github.com/aDrz/adrz.github.io/raw/master/content/images/rplot-compress.pdf">rplot-compress.pdf</a> (16 Ko).</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[50 years of avengers comic book covers though color]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://graphics.wsj.com/avengers">http://graphics.wsj.com/avengers</a></p>]]></description><link>http://iwoaf.com/50-years-of-avengers-comic-book-covers-though-color/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">803bf360-f11c-4087-9e58-c8553cad0e3e</guid><category><![CDATA[external]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[aDrz]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 13:23:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://graphics.wsj.com/avengers">http://graphics.wsj.com/avengers</a></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[podcast about drinking, data-science and awesomeness]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.partiallyderivative.com/">http://www.partiallyderivative.com/</a></p>]]></description><link>http://iwoaf.com/podcast-about-drinking-data-science-and-awesomeness/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">3d113dba-7621-4c9d-94eb-06d75498128f</guid><category><![CDATA[external]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[aDrz]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2015 13:20:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.partiallyderivative.com/">http://www.partiallyderivative.com/</a></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[my old movie gifs part 1/3]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I recently find my old movie gifs that I published in my preivous blog. It would be unfortunate to see them desappear. So here is my collection. Highly influenced by <a href="http://iwdrm.tumblr.com/">if we don't remember, me</a> and <a href="http://technoir.nl/">technoir</a></p>

<p><strong>American Beauty</strong> (1999):</p><p> 
<img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/08/americanbeauty.gif" alt="drawing"></p>

<p><strong>Beerfest</strong> (2006):</p><p> 
<img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/08/beerfest_thumb.gif" alt="drawing"></p>

<p><strong>Chronicle</strong> (2012):</p><p> 
<img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/08/chronicle_thumb.gif" alt="drawing"></p>

<p><strong>Night on Earth</strong> (1991):</p><p> 
<img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/08/night_on_earth.gif" alt="drawing"></p>

<p><strong>Hugo</strong> (2011)</p>]]></description><link>http://iwoaf.com/my-old-movie-gifs-part-13/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">1f05f39a-488c-4e4f-8670-4be5fd71e6f8</guid><category><![CDATA[gif]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[aDrz]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2015 13:19:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I recently find my old movie gifs that I published in my preivous blog. It would be unfortunate to see them desappear. So here is my collection. Highly influenced by <a href="http://iwdrm.tumblr.com/">if we don't remember, me</a> and <a href="http://technoir.nl/">technoir</a></p>

<p><strong>American Beauty</strong> (1999):</p><p> 
<img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/08/americanbeauty.gif" alt="drawing"></p>

<p><strong>Beerfest</strong> (2006):</p><p> 
<img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/08/beerfest_thumb.gif" alt="drawing"></p>

<p><strong>Chronicle</strong> (2012):</p><p> 
<img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/08/chronicle_thumb.gif" alt="drawing"></p>

<p><strong>Night on Earth</strong> (1991):</p><p> 
<img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/08/night_on_earth.gif" alt="drawing"></p>

<p><strong>Hugo</strong> (2011):</p><p> 
<img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/08/hugo.gif" alt="drawing"></p>

<p><strong>Breakfast at Tiffany's</strong> (1961):</p><p> 
<img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/08/breakfastattiffanys.gif" alt="drawing"></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[how fast does miles teller play in whiplash?]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="video-container">  
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/0IzlhHz6UKg" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>  
</div>

<p>Released at the end of 2004, <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2582802/">Whiplash</a> focuses on a promosing young drummer (Miles Teller) poursuying his  dreams of greatness. This greatness will only be achieved with the help of a ruthless teacher (J. K. Simmons) that will push him to his limits. Obviously classic but I strongly recommend the</p>]]></description><link>http://iwoaf.com/how-fast-does-miles-teller-play-in-whiplash/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">d536f602-1fa6-40a8-9a79-e126ebaf2ae6</guid><category><![CDATA[movie]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[aDrz]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2015 13:18:34 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="video-container">  
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/0IzlhHz6UKg" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>  
</div>

<p>Released at the end of 2004, <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2582802/">Whiplash</a> focuses on a promosing young drummer (Miles Teller) poursuying his  dreams of greatness. This greatness will only be achieved with the help of a ruthless teacher (J. K. Simmons) that will push him to his limits. Obviously classic but I strongly recommend the movie.</p>

<p>I am unfortunatly not a musician, nor an enlightened enthusiast, so what strikes me the most is the strong hability of Miles Teller to play quite fast. I do enjoy the overall portraying of the jazz education and the sadistic teacher/student relationship but at the end of the movie, I just needed to know if the performance of the actor in term of quickness was impressive. That is why I consider analysing the audio from the first and the last scenes of Whiplash to extract how fast does Miles Teller play and compare it with the actual World's Fastest Drummer.</p>

<p>The metric used is the Beat Per Minutes (BPM) which, in the case of the drum, simplified to how many times the drummer hits his instrument per minutes. This BPM is estimated by the detection of a short transcient peaks in the audio signal then the difference of time between two consecutive peaks allows the computation of the <em>instantaneous BPM</em>. The two following figures shows the basic idea and problem behind the detection of these short peaks (beat) in an audio signal. The red dots represents a detection and the numbers between two consecutive dots are the <em>instantaneous BPM</em>. The first figure is an example of clear identifiable beats with an slightly increasing BPM (311 - 323 - 336 - 361 - ...). However the the second example exhibits the problem that arises when beats are pretty closed to each others leading to the end of a beat signal interfering with the beginning of the next one. So it makes the estimation of the <em>instantaneous BPM</em> harder and thus more noisy.</p>

<p><img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/03/beat-detect-low.png" alt="xwf">
<img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/03/beat-detect-high.png" alt="wfkj"></p>

<p>Now let's see how the Miles performs in the first see of the movie. The x-axis is the number of the beats. For the first scene, around ~200 beats were detected. For those who haven't seen the movie, in the first scene Miles starts playing and slowly accelerate the rythm. The acceleration is clearl on the graph, he starts with less that 100 beats per minutes and ends with ~900 beats per minutes.</p>

<p><img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/03/bpm-whiplash-beginb-1.png" alt="whiplash-bpm-first-scene"></p>

<p>The BPM of the final scene has also been studied (from 2:36 to 3:56 of the embedded video). On this scene, the algorithm probably missed few drum beats as even if Miles Teller is at his higher beat rate (end of the graph) some <em>instantaneous BPM</em> appears to be around 450 quite precisely half of what the other points concentrate at that moment (between 800 and 1000). I like how the evolution of the <em>instantaneous BPM</em> draws a V shape, with a regular decrease then an as regular increase. So to answer the title-question "how fast does miles teller play in whiplash?", I will answer with <strong>900 BPM</strong> (±25).</p>

<p><img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/03/bpm-whiplash-end-1.png" alt="whiplash-bpm-last-scene"></p>

<p>Trully fast in my opinion. But let's compared it with the actual world's fastest drummer. I confronte the beat detection algorithm to the known world record of 1208 beat in one minute <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Q9FrW-Wr-ds">video of the record</a>. The algorithm detects <strong>1211</strong> beats instead of <strong>1208</strong> !  The <em>instantaneous BPM</em> of this record is of interest as we see that the drummer varies between 1000 and 1700 over the whole one minute of the drum session. We might account this variation to both the algorithm and the drummer himself. However, he seems incredibly constant even if a linear regression tells us that he starts with a <em>instantaneous BPM</em> of <strong>1282</strong> (±26) and finishes with <strong>1193</strong> (±26).</p>

<p><img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/03/bpm-wfd-1.png" alt="world-fastest-drummer-bpm"></p>

<p>And finally, let's look at the BPM of the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZpknwYRp7uY">challenge</a> given by the World's Fastest Drummer to Miles Teller. He seems to rise up to <strong>1100</strong> BPM.</p>

<p>But as Miles <a href="http://radio.com/2015/03/13/miles-teller-worlds-fastest-drummer-response/">said</a> “Why would you challenge a guy who played in some garage bands in Florida and has a fun time doing it? I don’t go for speed. It’s not a sprint for the Miles man.”</p>

<p><img src="http://iwoaf.com/content/images/2015/03/bpm-wfdchallenge.png" alt="world-fastest-drummer-bpm-challenge"></p>

<p>The code and the waveform are available here!</p>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>